Guide to the Records of The New York Institute for the Humanities RG.37.4
New York University Archives
- Series III. Audio and Video Recordings, 1974-2010
  - Subseries IIIA. Cassette Tapes, 1974-2005
    - Catherine Stimpson, "Gertrude and Her Politics", 16-Oct-98; cuid4042 (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - Hal Foster, "The State of Criticism", 23-Oct-98; cuid4043 (Box 65, Folder 5)
    - Jane Gallop, "Resisting Reasonableness: Consensual Amorous Relations, Pedagogy, and Conflict of Interest", 30-Oct-98; cuid4044 (Box 65, Folder 6)
    - Tom Bishop, "Unblocking Memory for a Memoir", 6-Nov-98; cuid4045 (Box 65, Folder 7)
    - Jerome Bruner, "Inventing Infancy", 20-Nov-98; cuid4046 (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - Shashi Tharoor, "On India", 11-Dec-98; cuid4047 (Box 65, Folder 9)
    - Linda Nochlin, "The Modernity of Mary Cassatt", 5-Feb-99; cuid4048 (Box 65, Folder 10)
    - Rosalind Krauss, "On Jackson Pollock", 5-Feb-99; cuid4049 (Box 65, Folder 11)
    - Lawrence Weschler, "The Exile and Calamitous Return of Breyten Breytenbach", 9-Feb-99; cuid4050 (Box 65, Folder 12)
    - Ari Zolberg, "Immigration and the Future of the Nation State", 26-Feb-99; cuid4051 (Box 65, Folder 13)
    - David Rieff, "Humanitariansim and the Human Rights: Convergence and Contradictions", 5-Mar-99; cuid4052 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    - Morris Dickstein, "Roots of the Counter Culture", 12-Mar-99; cuid4053 (Box 66, Folder 2)
    - Jerry Siegel, "What is Bourgeois Individualism", 9-Apr-99; cuid4054 (Box 66, Folder 3)
    - Leonard Barkan, "A Circle of Shades", 16-Apr-99; cuid4055 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    - Leonard Barkan, "A Circle of Shades", 16-Apr-99; cuid4056 (Box 66, Folder 5)
    - Robert Paxton, "Vichy in the Courtoom: The Trial of Maurice Papon", 30-Apr-99; cuid4057 (Box 66, Folder 6)
    - Particia Williams, "The Emperor's New Clothes", 30-Apr-99; cuid4058 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    - Arnold Steinhardt, "The Courtesan and the Violinist", 24-Sep-99; cuid4059 (Box 67, Folder 1)
    - Mary Poovey, "NYIH and Interdisciplinarity at NYU", 1-Oct-99; cuid4060 (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - Urvashi Vaid, "Toward a New Coalition in the Gay and Lesbian Movement", 15-Oct-99; cuid4061 (Box 67, Folder 3)
    - Terry Riley, "Rethinking Critical Space: Redesigning the Museum of Modern Art", 22-Oct-99; cuid4062 (Box 67, Folder 4)
    - Tony Hiss, "The View from Alger's Window", 29-Oct-99; cuid4063 (Box 67, Folder 5)
    - David Denby, "James Agee in 1945: Movies and Criticism Now", 5-Nov-99; cuid4064 (Box 67, Folder 6)
    - Troy Duster, "The Racialization of Politics and the Politicization of Race", 12-Nov-99; cuid4065 (Box 67, Folder 7)
    - Stephen Jay Gould, "Questioning the Millennium", 19-Nov-99; cuid4066 (Box 67, Folder 8)
    - Charles Halpern, "On Y2K: Reflections at the End of the Millennium", 3-Dec-99; cuid4067 (Box 67, Folder 9)
    - Joan Acocella, "Editing Nijinsky's Diary", 10-Dec-99; cuid4068 (Box 67, Folder 10)
    - Nicholas Lemann, "Meritocracy in America", 4-Feb-00; cuid4069 (Box 67, Folder 11)
    - Richard Sennett, "Work and Its Discontents", 11-Feb-00; cuid4070 (Box 67, Folder 12)
    - Peter Singer, "The Sanctity of Life", 18-Feb-00; cuid4071 (Box 67, Folder 13)
    - Rayna Rapp, "Gender and Genomes: An Anthropological Perspective on How New Genetic Knowledge Gets Made and What Happens to It", 3-Mar-00; cuid4072 (Box 67, Folder 14)
    - Jonathan Schell, "On the Presidential Primaries", 10-Mar-00; cuid4073 (Box 67, Folder 15)
    - Mary Ellen Burns, "From Dot-dash to Dot-com: Prespectives on the Past and future of the Internet", 24-Mar-00; cuid4074 (Box 67, Folder 16)
    - Komar and Melamid, "Art and Collaboration: Other Artists, Other Species", 31-Mar-00; cuid4075 (Box 67, Folder 17)
    - Lydia Davies, On Translating Proust, 7-Apr-00; cuid4076 (Box 67, Folder 18)
    - Betty Fussell, "The Meaning of the Kitchen", 14-Apr-00; cuid4077 (Box 67, Folder 19)
    - Michael Cunningham, "Virginia Woolf and Chaos Theory: Time, Synchronicity, and Other Impossible Problems in the Novel", September 22, 2000; cuid4078
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 1)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:52)
    - Doug Guthrie, "The End of History? Political, Economic and Social Change in China", September 29, 2000; cuid4079
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 2)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:53)
    - Jessica Yu, "A Cast of Trillions: The Art of Henry Darger", October 6, 2000; cuid4080
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 3)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:54)
    - Daniel Pipes, "The Current Crisis in the Middle East", October 13, 2000; cuid4081
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 4)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:55)
    - Breyten Breytenbach, "Notes from the Middle World", October 20, 2000; cuid4082
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 5)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:56)
    - Colm Toibin, "The Legacy of Coole: Lade Gregory, Sir William Gregory, and the Creation of an Irish National Identity", October 27, 2000; cuid4083
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 6)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:57)
    - Philip Gourevitch, "Black and White and Gray Over: Some Thoughts on the Problems and Politics of Journalistic Evenhandedness", November 3, 2000; cuid4084
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 7)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:58)
    - Robert Krulwich, "Panic in the News Room", November 10, 2000; cuid4085
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 8)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:59)
    - Fred Siegel, "Mayors and Morality: Daley and Lindsay, Then and Now", November 17, 2000; cuid4086
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 9)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:60)
    - Edward Rothstein, " Music and Masterpieces: Why Audiences Love the 19th Century", December 1, 2000; cuid4087
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 10)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:1)
    - Bruce Chilton, "The Rabbi's Revenge, The Story of Jesus", December 8, 2000; cuid4088
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 11)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:2)
    - Noelle Oxenhandler, "The Eros of Parenthood: Explorations in Light and Dark", January 9, 2001; cuid4089
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 12)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:3)
    - Mark Salzman, "Why I Love the Bach Cello Suites: A Talk and Performance", February 2, 2001; cuid4090
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 13)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:4)
    - Robert Hollander, "Justice and Poetry: Dante's Book of the Dead", February 16, 2001; cuid4091
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 14)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:5)
    - Kenneth Frampton, "Megaform as Urban Landscape", February 23, 2001; cuid4092
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 15)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:6)
    - Roald Hoffmann, "The Royal Purple and the Biblical Blue: A Story of Religion, Protochemistry and Politics", March 2, 2001; cuid4093
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 16)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:7)
    - Michael Wood, "The Interpretation of Oracles: The Irrational and Its Reasons", March 9, 2001; cuid4094
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 17)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:8)
    - Herbert Leibowitz, "Parnassus at 25: Some Night Thoughts of an Editor on Poets, Poetry and the Decline of Literary Language", March 23, 2001; cuid4095
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 18)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:9)
    - Elizabeth Holtzman, "The Election and the Court", March 30, 2001; cuid4096
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 19)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:10)
    - Martin Kace, "Coma and After", April 6, 2001; cuid4097
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 20)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:11)
    - Claudia Roth Pierpont, "On Lincoln Kirstein", April 20, 2001; cuid4098
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 21)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:12)
    - Francine du Plessix Gray, "Loving and Hating Simone Weil", April 27, 2001; cuid4099
      - Original Recording (Box 68, Audiocassette 22)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 115, Cd 12:13)
    - Post-Lecture Lunch Discussion on Music Theory and Research with Steve Reich., 23-Apr-82; cuid4100; 1 audiocassettes; Tape contains approximately 47 minutes of audio on one side; Tape label: Steve Reich lunch 4/23/82. (Box 69, Folder 1, Box Shared University Archives 108, Item 25)
      Recorded on one side of a TDK Normal Bias, D-C90 audio cassette.
      This recording appears to be of conversation over lunch after a lecture. Steve Reich and others discuss music theory and his research for the lecture he has already given. (See related materials note)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 5:25.
      Related materials
      Steve Reich gave a lecture shortly before this lunch discussion. It is available as part of this collection (Discussion with Steve Reich: A "New American Music Series" Gallatin Lecture, Box 75, Folder 9).
      New York Institute for the Humanities; Reich, Steve, 1936-
    - War in Bosnia. A Discussion with David Rieff, 25-Feb-93; cuid4101; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 90 minutes; Business card of Jocelyn Eklof Carlson, New York Institute for the Humanities found in case with cassette.; Audio quality is very good due to the small space in which recording was made and proximity of microphone to speakers; Tape label: FEB 25, 1993 BOSNIA; Each side of the tape contains approximately 47 minutes of audio. (Box 69, Folder 2, Box Shared University Archives 108, Item 26, Item 27)
      Access copy available on 2 CDS: ACCESS 5:26 & ACCESS 5:27.
      Lecture recorded on both sides of a maxell Communicator Series C90 cassette tape.
      David Rieff, just returned from Bosnia, discusses the war conditions and experience of the Bosnian people. A little less than half of the recording is Rieff giving his talk, then it is opened up to questions. While there is some back and forth/conversation from the small group, this Q&A is still predominantly Rieff giving very detailed answers to questions.
      New York Institute for the Humanities; Yugoslav War, 1991-1995 -- Personal narratives, Bosnian; Sarajevo (Bosnia and Hercegovina); War stories, Bosnian; United Nations. Security Council.; Rieff, David
    - Symposium on Science and the Humanities with Denis Donoghue and Gerald Holton, 31-Oct-86; cuid4102; 1 audiocassettes Approximately 73 minutes; Approximately 47 minutes of audio on Side A, 26 minutes of audio on Side B; Audio quality is good, though there is a roomtone hiss throughout; Insert label: 10/31/86, Denis Donahue and Gerald Holton; (Box 69, Folder 3, Box Shared University Archives 108, Item 28)
      Recorded on both sides of a TDK "High Position Type II SA90, High Bias 70μs EQ, Super Avilyn Cassette.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 5:28
      Mallinckrodt Research Professor of Physics at Harvard University, Gerald Holton and Henry James Chair of English and American Letters at New York University, Denis Donoghue present brief lectures on the measures of progress in their varying fields. The program was designed as a way of bringing prominent members of the science and humanities communities together in a single venue and treat the lectures as a means of conversation between the two which are sometimes seen as oppositional to each other. The program is moderated by a man only once referred to by name as "Will." Holton and Donoghue speak for about 20 minutes each. The remaining half-hour is dedicated to Q&A with them both.
      Literary criticism (New York, N.Y.); Literature/literary criticism; Humanities; Science and the humanities; Physics -- Study and teaching -- United States; New York Institute for the Humanities; Donoghue, Denis; Holton, Gerald James
    - Daniel Bell and Susan Sontag Tape 1, December 12, 1994; cuid4103
      - Original Recording (Box 69, Audiocassette 4)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:10, 11:11)
    - Daniel Bell and Susan Sontag Tape 2, December 12, 1994; cuid4104
      - Original Recording (Box 69, Audiocassette 5)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:12)
    - Symposium on Conservatism, Liberalism, and Intellectualism with Paul Starr and Robert L. Heilbroner, 8-Feb-95; cuid4105; 1 audiocassettes Approximately 82 minutes; Audio quality is good; Approximately 47 minutes of audio on Side A, approximately 35 minutes of audio on Side B Insert label: Paul Star 2/8/95 1/1 copy. (Box 69, Folder 6, Box Shared University Archives 108, Item 29, Item 30)
      Recorded on both sides of a 3M AVX90, Normal Bias Professional Cassette.
      Access copy available on two CDs: ACCESS 5:29 & ACCESS 5:30.
      Pulitzer Prize-winning professor of sociology and public affairs at Princeton University Paul Starr and American economist, historian of economic thought and author of The Worldly Philosophers: The Lives, Times and Ideas of the Great Economic Thinkers (1953), Robert L. Heilbroner give lectures on liberalism, conservatism and intellectualism. Starr speaks for about 30 minutes on the shift of conservative disdain of outright Communisim and Socialism to basic democratic liberalism as being seen as a threat to American ideals. Heilbroner speaks for only about 10 minutes on intellectualism and it's relationships to both liberalism and conservativism. The remaining 30-40 minutes are dedicated to Q&A and conversation between the two. The program is moderated by a man referred to only once as "Michael."
      Conservatism; Liberalism; Radicalism; Socialism; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Health care reform; Welfare rights movement; Contemporary politics; Heilbroner, Robert L.; Starr, Paul, 1949-
    - Roundtable on Commercial Culture and the Working Class in 19th Century Paris, 3-Oct-86; cuid4106; 1 audiocassettes Approximately 73 minutes; Audio quality is good; Approximately 47 minutes of audio on Side A, approximately 26 minutes of audio on Side B; Insert label: Oct 3, 1986 COMMERCIAL CULTURE; (Box 69, Folder 7, Box Shared University Archives 108, Item 31)
      Audio recorded on both sides of a TDK Normal Position, Type I, D90 Dynamic Cassette - normal EQ 120μs.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 5:31.
      Round table conversation of unnamed participants, on the working class and its relationship with commercial culture and art in the 19th century. A good portion of the conversation revolves around T.J. Clark's book, The Painting of Modern Life: Paris in the Art of Manet and His Followers. The formal conversation ends about 5 minutes before the recording and that time is filled with layered banter between the participants.
      Paris (France) |x Intellectual life |y 19th century.; Realism in art; Impressionist (style); realism (artistic form of expression); Paris (France) -- History.; Paris (France); bourgeoisie; Working class; Artists.; Art.; Impressionism (Art); Manet, Édouard, 1832-1883; Clark, T. J. (Timothy J.)
    - The Operas of Philip Glass, 30-Apr-82; cuid4107; 1 audiocassettes; Approximately 47 minutes of audio on Side A, approximately 18 minutes of audio on Side B; Tape label: 4/30/82 Philip Glass luncheon; Case label: Philip Glass 4/30/82 (Box 69, Folder 8, Box Shared University Archives 108, Item 32)
      Recorded on both sides of a TDK D-C90 Cassette - Normal Bias EQ-120μs.
      Philip Glass discusses his work as a "composer who writes operas" and his incorporation of historical personages such as Albert Einstein, Mahatma Gandhi, and Eadweard Muybridge.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 5:32
      Opera.; Gandhi, Mahatma, 1869-1948; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904; Glass, Philip
    - Round Table Discussion on Architecture of Urban Cultural Centers, 17-Apr-79; cuid4108; 1 audiocassettes Approximately 1 hour, 20 minutes; Approximately 60 minutes of audio recorded on Side A, approximately 41 minutes of audio recorded on Side B; Insert label: Architecture of urban cultural centers 4/17/79, No Transcription; Audio quality is good, but there are static problems at the very beginning of each side. (Box 69, Folder 9, Box Shared University Archives 108, Item 33, Item 34)
      Recorded on both sides of a TDK Extended Range Low Noise High Aoutput AD-C120 "Audua" Cassette - Normal bias - EQ 120μs.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 5:33 & ACCESS :5:34
      Philip Johnson (architect of the New York State Theater and Lincoln Center), Richard Gilman (drama critic), Ellen Stewart (founder/director of LaMama tTheater) and Paul Goldberger (New York Times architecture critic) discuss the relationship between cultural spaces, the various "publics" that use them, and the art and cultural materials/identities that are produced as a result of them. Speakers present a brief statement and then engage in discussion with each other and the audience.
      La Mama Theatre; Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts; Ellen Stewart Theatre (Organization: New York, N.Y.); Cultural centers; performing arts centers; Culture.; Goldberger, Paul; Stewart, Ellen, 1919-2011; Johnson, Philip, 1906-2005; Gilman, Richard, 1923-2006
    - Forum on Public Art in the City, 20-Nov-78; cuid4109; 1 audiocassettes (Box 69, Folder 10, Box Shared University Archives 108, Item 35, Item 36)
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 3:35 & ACCESS 3:36
      Recorded on both sides of a TDK D-C120 Dynamic Cassette - normal bias, EQ 120 μs.
      Participants include sculptor Robert Murray, painter Janet Henry, and architect Kenneth Frampton.
    - Creating the Book "Aftermath: World Trade Center Archive"-- Lecture by Photographer Joel Meyerowitz, May 13, 2002; cuid4110; 2 audiocassettes Approx. 100 minutes.; The first tape has approximately 46 minutes of content on each side. The speaker pauses throughout and there is the sound of material brushing against the mircrophone. The second tape has only the conclusion, approximately ten minutes of content.
      Recorded on three sides of two Sony audiocassette tapes.
      After lengthy introductions by NYU President John Sexton and Lawrence Weschler, the lecture begins about 18 minutes into the recording. Photographer, Joel Meyerowitz discusses his work creating a photographic archive of the aftermath of the September 11, 2001 attacks on the World Trade Center which culminated with his book, Aftermath: World Trade Center Archive.
      General
      Tape 2 was formerly logged as a separate intellectual entity: ref2249
      September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Photographers -- United States.; Joel Meyerowitz book; Photography; Photographs.; Weschler, Lawrence; Sexton, John Edward, 1942-; Meyerowitz, Joel, 1938-
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 2)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 110, Cd 7:19 - 7:21)
    - Episodes of This American Life and All Things Considered (Tony Grafton Discusses Kircher Symposium), May 22, 2002; cuid4111; 1 audiocassettes; Labels conflict with each other. Insert label: Weschler on Toch; Tape Label: Tony Grafton on Kircher ATC May 22, 2002.
      The Kircher symposium which Grafton discusses was recorded and is available as part of this collection (The Life and Work of Athanasius Kircher, Box 72, Folder 5).
      Side A has the episode of the NPR show This American Life, "Pimp Anthology". Side B holds a 2004 episode of "All Things Considered," also on NPR. Judging by one of the labels (Tony Grafton on Kircher ATC May 22, 2002), the content that was targeted as the intended recording begins at 18:27 on side B (Or ACCESS CD 7:23). Anthony Grafton discusses a NYIH symposium on the life of Athanaseus Kircher. The story can actually be found here: http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=1143769. (See related materials note for symposium)
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 4)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 110, Cd 7:22, 7:23)
    - The Life and Work of Athanasius Kircher, Symposium, May 23, 2002; cuid4112; 2 audiocassettes Approx 3 hours
      A NYIH symposium on Athanaseus Kircher. Princeton University professor Anthony Grafton hosts and leads the lectures. Grafton discusses Kircher in general terms, then focuses on how Kircher thought about history, tradition, and the past, particularly Kircher's thoughts on how the Egyptian tradition was recorded in hieroglyphs. Next, Paula Finland discusses Kircher as a global figure, focusing on his deep and intimate connections around the world maintained through correspondence. After Finland, Michael John Gorman discusses Kircher the "engineer and magician", the creater of magnificent machines. Finally, David Wilson "channels" Kircher to close things out.
      Recorded on two maxell Professional "Communicator Series C90" audiocassettes.
      Tape 2 was formerly logged as a separate intellectual entity: ref2254
      Tony Grafton discussed the symposium on an episode of "All Things Considered" on NPR. The episode was recorded and is available as part of this collection (Episodes of This American Life and All Things Considered - Tony Grafton Discusses Kircher symposium, Box 72, Folder 4).
      Hieroglyphics; Wilson, David Hildebrand, 1946-; Finland, Paula; Gorman, Michael John; Kircher, Athanasius, 1602-1680; Grafton, Anthony
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 5)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 110, Cd 7:24 - 7:27)
    - Rhapsodic Non-Fiction: A Conversation between Ryszard Kapuscinski and Oliver Sacks, September 18, 2002; cuid4113; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 90 minutes; Channel shifting noted on both sides (somewhat more prominent at the beginning of side 2).
      Recorded on both sides of a maxell Communicator C90 Series audiocassette.
      Introduced by Lawrence Weschler, this is a recording of a conversation between Ryszard Kapuscinski and Oliver Sacks that took place at Hemmerdinger Hall on September 18, 2002; an event entitled Rhapsodic Non-Fiction. Weschler explains the title by pointing out a common thread in the seemingly very different authors' works. Kapuscinski's The Emporer, on the surface was about an an anti-communist, Ethiopian regime being toppled, but was allegorical to the situation in Poland in the late 1970s. Oliver Sacks' Awakenings was about his patients with "locked in" syndrome, but could be compared to the result of liberation of nations, such as Poland and Czechoslovakia, previously trapped under strict authoritarian rule.
      Communism.; Psychology.; Poland; Psychology and philosophy; Psychology |x Cases, clinical reports, statistics.; Sacks, Oliver, 1933-2015; Kapuściński, Ryszard; Weschler, Lawrence
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 7)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 110, Cd 7:28, 7:29)